Guide to the Mendel V. Halushka Papers TAM.022
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mendel V. Halushka Papers
1919-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Halushka, Mendel V., 1904-1958
Halushka, Sally
TAM.022
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Chicago Socialist, compiler of list of Socialist publications, 1900-1950. The papers contain correspondence including letters from socialist notables, material relating to the Young People's Socialist League; a scrapbook of articles by Halushka and others; a scrapbook relating to the Young Circle League; and survey forms and charts relating to Halushka's research on Socialist mayors and Socialist newspapers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sally Halushka, widow of Mendel V. Halushka, 1959. The accession number associated with this gift is 1959.001.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Chicago Socialist, compiler of list of Socialist publications, 1900-1950.
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain original manuscripts and printed sources; correspondence concerning routine office, subscription and publication matters; several letters of interest from such socialist figures as William E. Bohn, Theodore Debs, Harry Laidler, Alfred Baker Lewis, Lena Morrow Lewis, James Oneal, Fred D. Warren and John M. Work; other correspondence and scrapbooks concerning socialist youth movements, particularly Young People's Socialist League and Young Circle League (Youth Clubs of Workmen's Circle); also contains responses and compilations from hundreds of form letters, personal letters, and questionnaires sent out to establish definitive historical records of all socialist newspapers (1900-1950) and mayoralties in the United States.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files
Scrapbooks.; Mayors |z United States.; Newspaper publishing -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Questionnaires.; Lewis, Alfred Baker, 1897-; Work, John M. (John McClelland), 1869-1961.; Oneal, James, 1875-1962; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Debs, Theodore, 1864-1945; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; Socialist Party (U.S.); Lewis, Lena Morrow; Warren, Fred B.; Bohn, William E.; Young People's Socialist League; Young Circle League of America; Halushka, Sally
- Series I: Subject Files
  - Circulars from Publications, 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Foreign Language Newspapers Survey Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings (Halushka articles, others), 1925-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Mayors; Charts on, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Mayors Correspondence, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Mayors Individual Data Forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Newspapers Correspondence, 1948-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Newspapers Survey Forms & Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1953-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Newspapers Survey Forms: Alabama - Michigan, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Newspapers Survey Forms: Minnesota - Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Newspapers Survey Forms: Rhode Island - Wyoming, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Young Circle League Correspondence, 1929-1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Young Circle League Scrapbook, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)